# XIAOJIAN XU

## [Homepage] [Google Scholar] [Github] [Twitter] [Linkedin]

Department of Computer Science and Engineering 

Washington University in St. Louis

### About me

#### Current research

My current research pursues to combine computational imaging, optimization, and machine learning to enable new intelligent imaging technology for various imaging applications including denoising, deblurring, superresolution, image segmentation, optical microscopy, magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), radar, and autonomous driving, etc. My research efforts are taking place at two complementary levels: (a) the fundamental and mathematical aspects of imaging; (b) application-oriented projects in collaboration with researchers in medicine, biology, and computer vision.

#### Research interests

· Computational Imaging, Optimization, Deep Learning, Inverse Problems, Computer Vision, Signal Processing

## EDUCATION

Washington University in St. Louis (WUSTL), St. Louis, MO, USA

9/2017-6/2022 (expected)

Ph.D student in Computer Science (GPA: 3.87/4.00), advised by Dr. Ulugbek Kamilov

University of Electronic Science and Technology of China (UESTC), Chengdu, China

9/2014-6/2017

M.Eng in Communication & Information Engineering (Graduated with Honors)

University of Electronic Science and Technology of China (UESTC), Chengdu, China

9/2010-6/2014

B.Eng in Communication Engineering (GPA: 3.89/4.00)

## WORKING EXPERIENCE

### Facebook Reality Labs Research (FRLR)

5/2021-8/2021

Research intern with Dr. Brian Wheelwright

Seattle (remote)

 Built the ray-tracing model for peripheral display system in Oculus, solved its display calibration problem, and designed an efficient camera-to-display mapping for its real-time rendering using neural representation.

#### Mitsubishi Electric Research Laboratories (MERL)

5/2019-8/2019

Research intern with Dr. Hassan Mansour

Bostor

• Investigated in 3D tomographic imaging problems and solved the problem by proposing two distinct methods, model-based optimization and data-driven deep learning.

## AWARDS & HONORS

#### **Honors** Honored Ph.D student in Computer Science & Engineering department 2021 Outstanding Graduate Student 2017 **Scholarship** Graduate Student First-Rank Academic Scholarship 2016 Graduate Student Second-Rank Academic Scholarship 2015 Graduate Student First-Rank Academic Scholarship 2014 National Inspirational Scholarship 2013 People's First-Rank Scholarship 2012 National Inspirational Scholarship 2011

#### Others

• Third-prize of 'Internet+' Entrepreneurship Competition in Sichuan Province

2016

- Great Award of Intelligent City Technology Competition 2016 2015
- Award of Hackathon Programming Competition
- Second Prize of Electronic Design Competition in UESTC 2011

### SKILLS

- Languages: Python, Matlab, C, Java
- Skills: Optimization, Inverse problems, Tensorflow, Pytorch, Deep learning, Linux, TCP/IP

### Research Experience

### Model-based deep learning for imaging and vision

8/2020 - Present

Developed imaging-model-assisted learning methods such as unsupervised learning, self-supervised and unrolling framework for different imaging tasks with various noise corruption challenges ([1, 2, 6, 7, 9]).

## Learning-based optimization for imaging and vision

8/2020 - Present

 Extensively investigated in variants of Plug-and-Play priors (PnP) and Regularized by denoising (RED) approaches for various imaging tasks by combining the imaging models with the deep-learning priors, in both theory and practice ([3, 4, 5]).

### Compressed and stochastic algorithms for large-scale imaging

7/2018 - Present

 Investigated in large-scale imaging problems by developing stochastic variants of optimization- and learningbased algorithms with convergence guarantee ([6, 7, 10]).

### Some earlier research experience

3/2014 - 6/2017

- Intelligent home system design and development.
- Routing and resource scheduling algorithms for large-scale network software defined networks (SDN).

#### Publications

## **Preprints**

- [1] X. Xu et al., "Learning-based Motion Artifact Removal Networks (LEARN) for Quantitative  $R_2^*$  Mapping," arXiv:2109.01622 [eess], Sep. 2021, [Online]. Available: http://arxiv.org/abs/2109.01622
- [2] S. Kahali, S. V. V. N. Kothapalli, X. Xu, U. S. Kamilov, and D. A. Yablonskiy, "Deep-Learning-Based Accelerated and Noise-Suppressed Estimation (DANSE) of quantitative Gradient Recalled Echo (gGRE) MRI metrics associated with Human Brain Neuronal Structure and Hemodynamic Properties," bioRxiv, 2021, doi: 10.1101/2021.09.10.459810.

#### **Published**

(\* indicates equal contribution)

- [3] X. Xu, Y. Sun, J. Liu, B. Wohlberg, and U. S. Kamilov, "Provable Convergence of Plug-and-Play Priors with MMSE Denoisers," IEEE Signal Process. Lett., vol. 27, pp. 1280–1284, 2020.
- [4] X. Xu, J. Liu, Y. Sun, B. Wohlberg, and U. S. Kamilov, "Boosting the Performance of Plug-and-Play Priors via Denoiser Scaling," in 54th Asilomar Conf. on Signals, Systems, and Computers, 2020, pp. 1305–1312.
- [5] X. Xu\*, Y. Sun\*, Z. Wu\*, B. Wohlberg, and U. S. Kamilov, "Scalable Plug-and-Play ADMM With Convergence Guarantees," IEEE Trans. on Comp. Imag., vol. 7, pp. 849-863, 2021.
- [6] J. Liu, Y. Sun, W. Gan, X. Xu, B. Wohlberg, and U. S. Kamilov, "SGD-Net: Efficient Model-Based Deep Learning with Theoretical Guarantees," IEEE Trans. on Comp. Imag., vol. 7, pp. 598-610, 2021.
- [7] J. Liu, Y. Sun, W. Gan, X. Xu, B. Wohlberg, and U. S. Kamilov, "Stochastic Deep Unfolding for Imaging Inverse Problems," in IEEE Int. Conf. Acoustics, speech and signal process (ICASSP), 2021, pp. 1395-1399.
- [8] X. Xu, O. Dhifallah, H. Mansour, P. T. Boufounos, and P. V. Orlik, "Robust 3D Tomographic Imaging of the Ionospheric Electron Density," in 2020 IEEE Int. Geoscience and Remote Sensing Symposium (IGARSS), 2020, pp. 437-440.
- [9] J. Liu, Y. Sun, X. Xu, and U. S. Kamilov, "Image Restoration Using Ttal Variation Regularized Deep Image Prior," in 2019 IEEE Int. Conf. Acoustics, speech and signal process (ICASSP), 2019, pp. 7715–7719.
- [10] X. Xu and U. S. Kamilov, "SignProx: One-bit proximal algorithm for nonconvex stochastic optimization," in IEEE Int. Conf. Acoustics, speech and signal process (ICASSP), Brighton, UK, May 2019, pp. 7800–7804.

## INVITED TALKS

- SIAM Conference on Imaging Science, 7/2020
- UCLouvain, Image and Signal Processing Group Seminar, 9/2020
- Asilomar Conference on Signals, Systems, and Computers, 10/2021

### Professional Services

- Conferences reviewer: ISBI, ICASSP
- Journals reviewer: IEEE Transactions on Image Processing (TIP), IEEE Transactions on Computational Imaging (TCI), Optics Communications, Scientific Reports, Signal Processing

## TEACHING & SUPERVISION EXPERIENCE

### (Head) TA for Optimization

2019-2020

Assistant Instructor

St. Louis

Served as the head assistant instructor and guest lecturer for course "Optimization" and "Large-Scale Optimization for Data Science" and obtained high evaluation from students.

### Students supervision

7/2018-Present

Research Supervisor

St. Louis

#### Current students

- Eddie Chandler, "Inhomogeneity correction for MRI", now B.S. student at WUSTL
- Yixuan Luo, "Deep-learning-based image segmentation", now M.S. student at WUSTL
- Michael Kincheloe, "Reinforcement learning for MRI artifacts correction". now B.S. student at WUSTL Previous students
- Zhixin Sun, "Neural representation for MRI reconstruction", coming Ph.D student at WUSTL
- · Weijie Gan, "Fast MRI reconstruction and artifacts correction", now Ph.D student at WUSTL
- Jiarui Xing, "Deep-learning-based MRI artifacts correction", now Ph.D student at University of Virginia
- · Shiqi Xu, "Sparse Fourier ptychographic microscopy", now Ph.D student at Duke University
- Hao Tang, "Adversarially robust classifiers for image reconstruction", now M.S. student at WUSTL
- Ryogo Suzuki, "Unfolding networks for image restoration", now at Rakuten Group, Inc.
- \* Yukun Li, "Single image denoising", now at Baidu Inc.
- Fa Long, "Dictionary learning for image restoration", now at Tencent Inc.